by the way everybody who bought a quilt
40 people bought quilts at the ga for
poor kids in cutand do to go to school
and they sent you a
photo okay so I'm going to leave it up
here but it's very cute and I'd like to
congratulate Hector and myy and other
people
yeah so come see afterwards rejoicing is
a very important thing in something you
did right right my llama saw the quilt
and started crying and thought it was a
beautiful thing so anyway here we
go I'm going to read to you ksan Lama
jamyang M
lams born
1689 okay we're going to go through
his I think it's one of the most
important teachings you'll ever get so
try to screw on your thinking cup
okay and try to pay attention I know
it's not
easy which involves not talking
okay here we
go uh it's called unweaving the web for
possibilities he starts out by saying
there are so how do you see things when
you reach nirvana okay that's the big
question and I I never got it clear in
my mind I was always confused and he he
decided it was important to talk about
it also okay here we go there are four
ways to see a water pcture why do they
always talk about water pictures in
philosophy cuz every room had one
because there was no plumbing and the
the disciples had to go get buckets of
water and we had to do that so every
room has a water picture kyash right uh
so
anyway there are four ways you can can
see a water picture number one you can
see a water picture as being a water
picture okay that's number one number
two you can see a water picture as
coming from its own side I'm
sorry uh a water sorry I blew it already
number one is a water picture can appear
to be a water
picture and you can take it as a water
picture okay it can appear to be a water
picture you got to get this feeling okay
it's appearing to you as a water picture
and you take it as a water picture okay
that's possibility number one number
two a water picture can appear to be
coming from its own side and you can
take it as coming from its own side
that's another possibility okay what
does it mean coming from its own side
what's keeping the water piture up why
does the water pitch hold
water well there's some kind
of quality in clay I mean if Sanka would
say there's a combination of Earth
element and the other tvas you know
there's something in clay that allows it
to hold water you don't make water
pictures from Jello for example
cuz they don't hold water there's some
quality in clay that when you fire it it
will hold water and it won't leak okay
true we say
no we say no
okay there's nothing in
clay that that makes a water pitch hold
water okay if a water pcture holds water
it's because you offered water to
someone else in the
past okay we did a talk at
Princeton what couple days ago we tried
to get the physics department
there what's his name hawkins's
publisher came that was
enough 250 people came but no I didn't
have enough physicist but anyway we were
talking about this these issues you know
and science's view is incomplete
okay there's nothing in clay that can
cause a a pot to hold water okay you
have to get used to that idea it appears
that way it seems that
way and that's part of a Vidya and
that's why we suffer okay even things
like water pots glass call it your glass
bottle or your plastic bottle there's
nothing in
plastic that can hold
water you got to get used to that until
you get used to that you will have have
anger you will have procrastination you
will have judging other you will have
these claas okay it's relevant okay
number two says number two says the
water bottle the plastic of the water
bottle appears to have the ability to
hold water but it and you can take it
that way you can think that that's true
and science does okay you can think that
that's true and science does too okay
that's step number two step number three
you can figure
out
sorry it can suddenly appear to you that
the plastic in the water bottle doesn't
have in itself the capacity to hold the
water and you can take it that
way okay opposite of number two all
right you it can appear to you
someday that the water the plastic in
the water bottle does not itself have
the capacity to hold water and you can
take it that way got it okay by the way
that one is the opposite of number two
and it's emptiness it's emptiness it's
the absence of the capacity to hold
water in the
plastic okay in the plastic number three
says in the plastic there's no capacity
to hold water you could walk on water if
you perceived it
correctly you could change water into W
wine I heard a joke on NPR they said
Jesus walked into a bar and said give me
a give me a martini glass full of water
no give me a wine glass full of water
anyway uh you could change
the that's where the cities come from
comes from the understanding that the
plastic is
not the the capacity to hold the water
is not in the plastic it's coming from
you also okay that's interesting then
you can have cities
uh that's emptiness right the absence of
number two is number three got
it don't sneeze this is important
time demons always make people sneeze at
that time okay number
four
one day it may appear to you that the
fact that the plastic is able to hold
the water is actually a small luminous
image popping out of a karmic seed in
your own mind one day it will appear to
you that what you see is a tiny luminous
image cracking out of a vasana open
opening up in your own
mind okay and you will take it to be
that way got it it will appear finally
that your screaming
husband is a luminous
image spading out of a tiny karmic seed
in your own mind you will catch it one
day when you get good at your meditation
you will catch it and it's awesome it's
incredibly awesome you know you catch in
the mind the karmic seed cracking open
and you see your husband you see when
your husband is yelling at you it's a
tiny little luminous image that just
came out of a karmic seed in your own
mind and it's not even out there okay
that's awesome so one day you will see
the bottle that way and you will take it
that way got it we're talking about how
it appears and how you take it four
possibilities it appears as a water
bottle and you take it as a water bottle
it appears as a bottle which can hold
water and you take it as a bottle which
can hold water is that
wrong no it it's holding water if you
don't believe me come up I'll pour it on
your head okay it is holding water it
appears to be holding water and it is
holding water no problem number two it
appears to be holding water because
there's something in the plastic and I
take that to be true is that correct
no number three me I
grasp that the plastic ability to hold
the water is not in the
plastic and it it doesn't seem that way
anymore and I don't take it that way
anymore is that true that's a high state
of
realization then number four whatever
capacity it has to hold water is coming
out of a tiny karmic seed in my own mind
is that
true that's true number three if you
know Buddhist terminology is emptiness
number four is what POS positive
dependent origination okay it's how
stuff happens rather than how stuff is
not
happening got it it's subtle he didn't
mention it you have to figure it out
number three is how stuff is not
happening number four is how stuff is
happening okay that's
important now comes the interesting part
dang
uh
which of the four do we have at any
given stage in our spiritual
career okay which of those four do we
have in our mind at any given stage in
our spiritual career it's very beautiful
those of you who have more training you
should live with this thing you should
carry this around and read it on buses
and stuff until it's all tattered and
worn out it's it's extraordinary it's
extremely important
okay you can judge where you are from
this you can judge how close you are
from this okay here we
go until a person perceives emptiness
they can have the first two modes of
perception in their mind but not the
second
two let's go over it until the day you
see emptiness did he say
directly he didn't say but he means okay
just for your information
mostly until you see emptiness you can
have the first two modes of perception
but not the second two what's the first
one it seems to be a water bottle it
appears to be a water bottle and I take
it to be a water bottle that's okay we
all have that it appear the plastic
appears to have the ability to hold the
water in
itself independent of me
and I take it to be that way is that
correct no but until the day you see
emptiness directly you believe that and
so scientists struggle to make bottles
and find new new chains of molecules
which will make the bottle hold water
more and then people die in the desert
because the water bottle
broke and that proves that science is
mistaken because it doesn't take into
account human interaction with the
things they
invent which is where they derive their
power
from plastic holds water for now
penicillin worked for a while because of
people because of their goodness and not
because of any
chemicals it's profound it has profound
implications for medicine and archa Arch
Ure you know on it's it's really
profound I had two physicists were
freaking out last time I went to
princ you know and they're all excited
you
know why does a water bottle break and
people die for lack of that
water it's not in the it's not in the
plastic the plastic isn't changed okay
the power of the plastic is not in the
plastic it's very interesting okay and
until you understand that you will have
claas okay now until you see emptiness
directly can you have the second two
perceptions can it appear to not can it
appear that the power to hold the water
is not in the plastic and you take it to
be not in the plastic not until you see
emptiness can it appear to you that
thing that thing is popping out of a
karmic SE in your mind and you take it
as something which is popping out of a
kic SE in your mind not until you see
emptiness that's very interesting
okay actually just before you see
emptiness you can see that in the few
hours before but that doesn't count I
guess all right so until you the day you
see emptiness you are confined to the
first two modes of perception and one of
them
is grossly mistaken deadly mistaken it
it can kill you it will kill you okay
unless you figure it out okay that's
until tell now here's the interesting
part where I
struggle between the time I see
emptiness directly and the time I
achieve Nirvana how does it appear and
how do I take it got it this is a this
is why I brought this up this is an in
this is important okay here we go a
person who has perceived emptiness but
who has not yet reached enemy Destroyer
orot right or the eth bod SAA level
which which is Arad on a Mahayana track
okay those of you who know that stuff
it's Arad it's Nirvana on a Mahayana
track occurs at the eighth bodh level
okay so he's just talking about the same
thing from the time you see emptiness up
to the time you see Nirvana but you're
not a Buddha yet right up up to the time
you reach nirvana that person can have
all
four what are the four can they can the
bottle appear as a bottle to them and
they take it as a
bottle after they see emptiness yeah no
problem everybody can Buddha can okay it
is a bottle there's no problem
there can a person who perceived
emptiness already see the bottle can it
appear to them that the power to hold
the water is in the plastic and they
take it to be
true they can not intellectually but in
experience they can that's very
important okay after you see emptiness
directly and someone comes up to you and
says does the plastic and the bottle
have the power in itself independent of
you to hold water you will say no does
it appear to you that way yes do you
sometimes take it that way when you're
not being conscious and aware yes that's
why people who saw the emptiness but
haven't reached nirvana yet still have
83,00
97 claes no kidding that's the
difference you only remove three claes
at the time you see emptiness directly
when they're being mindful they
understand that the yelling husband is
coming from them clearly but when
they're not being mindful it fakes them
out okay that faking out is the only
meaning of Illusion in in Indian
spiritual literature okay get used to
that Maya we're not talking about that
tonight but that's the only meaning of
Maya that condition of being faked out
by your husband when he yelled loud
enough and your memory of having SE
emptiness directly
slipped and you still get angry cuz
you're not at Nirvana yet got it you saw
emptiness directly but you can still get
angry at your husband when you forget
where he's coming from what you saw you
for get what you saw got it okay so a
person who's seen emptiness directly but
hasn't reached nirvana yet can still
slip and they can have all four states
of mind sometimes it looks like it's
doesn't have its own power and they see
it that way and that's fine sometimes
they see the power in the bottle to hold
water coming from karmic seed in their
mind and it appears that way so they
have all four possibilities got
it just just nod your head you can go
home okay here we go I often tell people
that
uh from enemy Destroyer on this gets
sexy this is interesting for me this is
the answer to my question that I always
had from enemy Destroyer on up to to
buddhahood how many of the four can you
still have
okay things can appear to be coming from
their own side but we don't take them
that way
therefore these beings no longer have
number two but they have all the
rest I think more correctly you'd have
to say they have half of number two but
not all of number
two okay so a a person who has reached
nirvana the world is still trying to
trick them things still appear as if
they had some power in them but they
never never slip so the difference
between Nirvana and not reaching Nirvana
and
apparently the thing that can stop every
negative emotion in the human heart is
to stop misunderstanding where things
are coming from even though they still
seem that way got it very powerful you
can destroy anger forever jealousy
forever addiction
forever and still the world can be
seeming to be what it's not to you okay
you can but you don't buy it you never
buy it okay and an Arya person who's
seen emptiness
directly sometimes they buy it and
sometimes they don't buy it got it all
four but in our heart never has numbered
two you got to chew on that okay things
still seem tricky but they never fall
for it therefore they never have a
negative emotion
no one can upset an an Arun
impossible the the husband can scream
all night and they they're
like okay so you're coming from me
they're like this right we talked about
the other day you know that the reaction
of a spiritual person to someone
screaming at you is uh they're trying to
engage you visually right like look in
my face I'm screaming at you and you're
like know what' I do last
week why is he here you know like you're
your attention is on your
own behavior you know what did I do last
week to cause this guy I mean how can I
stop him you know you don't try to yell
back or or not yell back you just think
you know what did I what did I do last
week that created him and then you
stopped doing it next week right okay
guess what happens at
Enlightenment no as far as appearance
and taking
it it doesn't even appear anymore to be
coming from its own side it doesn't look
tricky to you anymore it's just the
no-brainer the husband never appears as
if he were coming from himself so
obviously you
don't take him that way so for an
enlightened person for a
Buddha it can't even appear the wrong
way anymore got it now those guys of
those of you who studied deceptive
reality and Ultimate Reality you can
appreciate it more deceptive means not
okay now he doesn't stop there and God
bless
him okay he doesn't stop there and God
bless him he answers one of the most
beautiful questions of of of Buddhism
okay you ready here you don't read it
look at me get a get a
lineage you can get the paper
later so can we say
that a Buddha never sees how things
could fool
people he says
no can they never see
things as they are seen by someone who
is
fooled
huh why
not
why yeah how would they teach us how
would they know our problems you see
they perceive how you perceive stuff the
wrong
way okay so we can't legally say in the
toras what do you call it the legalistic
thing Talman you can't you cannot
legally say that a Buddha is unaware of
how things appear in a tricky way
they're aware but that's not how they
they they never appear that way to them
they see how you see things as tricky
that answers huge amounts of questions
about Enlightenment how do they serve a
suffering being if they don't have the
karma to see suffering they see you
suffer they see how you see the world
even as they see you as a high Lev b
suff or as a Divine
being got it that ansers so many deep
questions you know that's that answers
so much you know how can they see
everybody as Divine and still serve them
as suffering
beings they see at the same time they
see you as Divine and at the same time
they see that you don't see yourself
that
way got it it's oh
man no
you
anyway we had to discipline a llama a
high llama
recently and and we all had to chew on
this I I handed it out you know it's
like can you see someone do something
naughty and discipline them at the same
time as you see them as a
l okay and the answer
is
yeah if you see somebody mugging a lady
you have to stop them he may be a the T
Daddy but you still have to stop them
right it's not
contradiction both are true okay got it
it's very subtle but it answers a lot of
life's problems okay you still have to
act in the world you still have to do
what's right even if the world is all
Divine beings okay you still can't stand
by while someone hurts another person
okay all
right
uh all right now uh you get uh 10
minutes of I'm going to tell you in 10
minutes how to remove the
claa that you you know it's very
beautiful okay uh and it's from my heart
and I pray that you try okay it's from
my heart I will know next time I come if
you did it or you didn't do it because
all I have to do is look at your face
you know I can tell who's happy and I
can tell who's not happy you can tell me
anything about your Mantra practice and
how many mantras you did and how many
layings you did I don't give a I don't
care it doesn't matter to me you know if
you don't look happy you're not
practicing and I don't care how many
mters you're doing and I don't care what
initiations you got cuz they're not
working okay if I see that you're
noticeably happier and I do you know I
go to many cities and then I come back
and in 6 months or a year and I see 10
people who are gleaming and shining and
happy and I say they're practicing they
got it then other people are telling me
Oh I got all these initiations and yeah
and I'm like yeah but you're obviously
irritating to everybody you know uh so
anyway
uh here's how we're going to stop our
our main claa okay and uh I'm sorry to
tell you I taught you during the ga
already it's a caric path right lyam you
must use the four steps okay you must
use the four steps I wrote them out for
you again you have them on a separate
reading okay that was also at
Starbucks
uh we took it from the teacher training
that we did last week we stole it and
modified it for
Nirvana okay uh four steps very quick
you do them you will get rid I will get
rid of my jealousy you'll get rid of
whatever it was and I don't need to tell
you more than that I'm not just trying
to skimp you because we ran out of time
it only takes 10 minutes whether you do
it is your problem and I can tell next
time I come okay uh those who remove
their number one claa become twice as
happy as they were before that's all
there is the rest is just dessert okay
here we go number one make a
statement what claa do you want to
remove and state its opposite right I
would like to stop my jealousy and I
would like to enjoy other people's
successes more okay I'll let you make a
sentence with an end in it which is
normally illegal in this
exercise okay but it's the same thing I
would like to stop my jealousy and I
would like
to appreciate what other people are
doing I would like to enjoy what other
people are doing I would like to stop
I'll give you all six right let's do
them fast I'd like to stop my anger and
become a person who cannot get
upset uh I would like to stop my
addictions and start enjoying the
opposite you know like if it's coffee I
would like to become a person who
appreciates a nice bottle of water which
is a skill which is a yogic skill
okay I would I would like to be a person
who doesn't need to eat a bunch of junk
food but who gets high on a few carrots
and thinks that's a wonderful thing like
has great pleasure from a few carrots
okay that's addiction okay the next one
I I I would like to be a person who no
longer judges other people but who
rather approaches everyone with the
assumption that they are divine and then
works out whatever they do from
that okay got it that's the opposite all
right there must be a reason why they're
you know taking the last ice cream
before me or you know probably they want
to protect me I mean a tantrica is
always interpreting things as some kind
of divine intervention in their life
that's part of what Tantra is okay uh
number five right
uh instead of being a person
who self self-imposed
busy uh I want to be a person who can be
contented when it's when when the time
is right I'd like to be the kind of
person who can sit on the porch and
watch the sunset the sun set for the
whole time it takes for the sun to set
and enjoy it without getting hyper and
thinking I have to go send an
email okay very few people have that
capacity you know there's Beauty
everywhere we don't have the capacity to
sit and watch it okay I would like to be
that and not self-imposed over busy okay
number six I I would like to be a person
who no longer procrastinates but who
rather you
know joyfully Chomps off the highest
priority thing that they're supposed to
do first you know prior procrastination
is all has to do with being un unwilling
to do the thing which is most important
first that's all I'd like to be a person
who goes after the difficult situations
you know in my position for example I
have people who have great
needs uh who are having personal
crisises in their life I would rather
translate a text it's it's more
interesting to me and it's more fun you
know I'm like God look at this you know
and then somebody's like Gish I'm going
to commit suicide I'm like just wait a
while
I but who's more priority what's the
higher priority I mean it's a human
being is always more important than a
text and then uh I would like so number
six I would like to be a person who does
the most important things first I would
like to change how I prioritize things
okay got it that's step number one state
what you
want step number two you must realize
that you cannot plant the seed by
yourself to plant the seeds to destroy
your own worst negative emotion you need
another person it's not possible by
yourself Lama likes
it l likes
it
okay
it's not possible to plant the seed to
destroy your negative Emotion by
yourself you must have another person
you must find another person who has the
same problem or a similar problem okay
you cannot do it by yourself not
possible okay that's just the way it is
number two means plan who you're going
to
help okay choose who you're going to
help that's number two make a plan I
have to find someone who has jealousy I
did it this today in Starbucks I was
like dang I never thought of that you
know I have to find someone else who's
jealous and help them get over
it and then I'll plant the seeds for me
to get over it that's the only way in
this system that's the only way so your
job is to find someone else who has the
same
one roughly there's a little leeway you
know okay you can be furious they can be
angry it's okay
uh all right find someone who has
jealousy who's Afflicted lady Ruth said
uh harassed I love that she said the
word harassed I'm going to remember that
CLA the definition is harassing the word
is harassing right so I must find
someone else who's harassed by that
emotion okay then make a plan still
number two okay still in number two I
will take them out to Starbucks I always
say Starbucks okay I will take them out
to
Starbucks and I will I will support them
you cannot solve their problems okay
it's not going to happen ultimately they
have to take someone else out to
Starbucks I'm buying stock in
Starbucks
okay but you can support them you can
give suggestions you can you can say I'm
in this with you I understand you have a
problem with jealousy by the way don't
go up to somebody that you don't know
very well and say I understand you're a
schmuck you know and I'm going to help
you out you know it's not going to work
very well but someone you're close to
you can say look you have the same thing
I do I have the same problem as you okay
let's help each other a good way to say
it is let's help each other not that I'm
going to help you let's let's have a
jealousy support group you know I'm not
kidding GUI Michael's jealousy support
group we're meeting tomorrow uh on the
beach
uh
so so anyway that's number
two understand that the actual helping
the other person which is Step
number three okay actually taking them
to Starbucks doesn't make as much karmic
seeds as the planting
does okay fantasizing which is my word
for
meditation on the bus about what you're
going to say and how you're going to
help them accumulates more karmic seeds
than the time at Starbucks okay and
people don't get that they don't know
that people come up to me all the time
and say I'm generous person I didn't
make a qu billion doll
then I'm like you didn't do number two
you did number three you didn't do
number two and you especially didn't do
number four
okay number three is you actually take
them to stomachs okay that's okay and
you support you just give them support
does it have to be every day
no once a week once every two weeks why
small seeds make big trees that's all
you don't have to go crazy don't do more
than you can do or you'll get grumpy and
you'll get worse okay do a modest tiny
little service sincerely to someone else
to help them with their jealousy when
you can and that's enough that plants a
seed and the seed will grow okay uh an
hour at Starbucks creates a lifetime
without jealousy okay I got it and
that's the way seeds are an O an acorn
weighs a half a gram uh a mature oak
tree weighs 350
tons and Karma is the same just help
them in the capacity that you have right
now help them once a week once every two
weeks you know don't go crazy cuz you'll
quit and you'll get grumpy about it
okay number four this is the most
important
one uh and we're almost going to end on
time so don't stress
uh after you come back from Starbucks
and you finish your day at work come
home cook your meal clean up do your
emails and TV whatever you got to do
which I don't support and then
um take your bath change into your night
clothes lay back on your bed like
that okay when you were daydreaming
about your boy boyfriend in high school
you
didn't you know there wasn't the
eight-point posture you know it was like
this right I'm a big proponent of
staring at the ceiling you know lay back
on your pillows on your bed and just you
know
relax and uh I saw guruji only in action
only a few times but he had this thing
relax
relax just relax
and uh look at the ceiling you know like
lay back on a bunch of pillows and and
look at the ceiling and say I planned to
take the person to
Starbucks I chose the person at step
number
two
uh then uh it's going to be a weird week
anyway uh and then in step three I
actually took them to Starbucks
even though it's not fun to take a
person to start okay it's not fun okay
you're not taking out your friend you're
taking out the most irritating person in
your
office okay get it I mean spiritual work
is done with people who are not fun and
it's good and that's the right thing to
do okay so then okay I took out this
irritating person they're jealous of
everybody not like me I'm just jealous
of some people and um you you know and
and uh I I gave them to some suggestions
I told them if they would just talk to
that person they're always jealous of if
they would sit together at Starbucks for
a few for an hour next to each other and
just smile and help each other their
life would be so much more pleasant you
know and they understood and they smiled
especially when I paid for the coffee
and
um and it went well and I'm proud of
myself okay I spent a couple hours with
someone that I I'm not very fond of and
who's not very lovable but I served them
and I help them with their jealousy
thing and I dedicate that to my own
jealousy I dedicate those karmic seeds
to curing my own jealousy okay and then
you will fall
asleep and that's the best way to make a
Karma grow your mind is very vulnerable
during During the period of sleep right
uh all night long your mind will work on
those seeds okay it will like number
crunching it will seed crunch all night
okay no it's a very beautiful process
okay most of us review the bad parts of
our day just before we go to bed and
then we sleep on that and it multiplies
and we dream about it and we wake up
grumpy right so in this system step four
is is extremely important as you lose
Consciousness on the bed you are
thinking about something good you did
for somebody else okay and it will
change your life okay you forget those
High tantric things okay I just gave you
something better all right go to bed as
you fall off to sleep think about the
kindnesses you have done for others okay
and and then your mind crunches that all
night and you wake up happy you wake up
well rested it's easier to fight claes
when you're well rested okay so that's
the four uh steps last thing last
homework question and last thing for
Nirvana
uh and by the way we're thinking I mean
we looked at our schedule today we want
to try to get back to New York we want
to do some things we want to do some
more of this kind of stuff maybe we
continue with Nirvana we would like to
do I spoke to uh I'm not a big friend of
daramet I mean I I what do you call I
adore him no I idolize him but I always
was afraid to talk to him so today we
had our longest conversation it was in
the elevator you know I'm like could I
come and do a two-day program and give
you all the money and he's like yep
and now because they need support they
they're starting a new center it's
expensive uh he's teaching by himself I
think all the classes and it breaks my
heart you know you know I see him tired
and I go for classes I love his classes
and so I want to do some kind of program
we've been talking about it for a while
actually so we'll do some kind of
program there for a couple days we'll do
a three jewels
program uh we'll continue with the chud
text right High secret stuff and then uh
we'll do a DCI program in New York we'll
do uh we'll start the 12 levels of uh
business programs in New York
uh so that'll all be I think start in
January why didn't I bring that
up
huh I don't remember
anyway
uh yeah but why did I talk about
that oh yeah the last step he's right
he's right let me see how that
relates I don't even know how that
relates anyway uh
anyway the last step look let's be uh
very honest here
um I give these talks all over the world
thousands of people come 1,200 people
are signed up for Moscow next week uh
pre-registered uh I'm going to tell them
for example that if they want to get a
good partner they
should go to a nursing home find a
lonely person and serve them right and
out of those 1,200 people one person
will I have a question for you then I'll
say what and they'll say what kind
of what kind of kindness is this it's
not kindness It's a business deal you
know I'll take care of your loneliness
if I can get a partner out of it I'll go
to the nursing home and visit a lonely
person if I can get a partner out of it
you know I'll give you some money if I
can get more back you see what I mean
I'll help you with your jealousy problem
if it will take care of mine and as soon
as mine's taken care of you know frankly
you can pay for your own
coffee no I mean somebody will ask this
question okay and it's true it's a good
question uh it comes in the beginning of
the mimik avatar the question comes if a
person performs Dona for selfish reasons
does it work and the answer is it does
it's a it's a law of the universe if you
give you shall receive okay but little
and lousy and inconsistent okay uh
there's another problem and I want to I
want you to know okay step three you go
to the nursing home to visit an elderly
lady
because you want to find a partner you
want to create a partner karmically and
by the way it works okay I got my own
lady I got an old lady for 20 years and
I'm very regular cuz I want it I want my
relationships to keep going you know I
want
my the people I perceive as a holy being
I want it to keep going I want that to
that's my fuel for that relationship uh
and I 20 years I haven't stopped
okay
anyway when you go visit the lady in the
nursing home you will create a partner
even if all you want is a partner and
you don't care about her you will get a
partner okay but that's selfish so
you're also planting a second
seat with your
motivation the partner you get is going
to be a selfish son of a
gun I'm not kidding so be careful okay
if the intention is is a business deal
I'll I'll take care of you if I can get
a partner you will get a partner and he
will use
you okay he will use
you in the same way you use the elderly
lady okay got it so you got to be super
careful how do you get around that how
do you want me to take care of that
there's a very simple thing it's called
bodh okay and it's very very very
beautiful so Buddhist always talking
about bodh his holiness transl
who I love we used to fight each other
in the debate ground he will say uh
something like Universal altruism or
something like that I like Wiz like dang
who's going to get Universal altruism
you know what does it mean universal
altruism when was the last time you saw
altruism used in a in English but anyway
um what is body
cheder is it like you have to sit down
and have a grand uh love for the
universe or something like
that bodh is what how do you define
it you have a vision for the world okay
means you have a vision for the world
what's the vision in this
case I
see
lines of young
ladies outside of nursing homes I I see
tickets with numbers on them you know
and they have to take a number because
Mrs Hancock's busy this week and we can
maybe fit you in Next Friday here's your
number here's your appointment time
she's busy in tell in thousands of young
hopeful ladies and young
men who want a partner are mobbing the
nursing homes I want to see a future in
this world
where every elderly person has two or
three younger people who are in love
with them and want to visit them every
day okay like that okay I want to see
that in the future that's the vision
right then as you are at the nursing
home helping the old lady you must think
the following train of thought and it
will be bodh ched and it's natural okay
if I get a fantastic partner after 5
years with no partner at all right right
and I bring him to the restaurant to
show him off to my girlfriends you okay
like you know you don't even mentioned
that you have a partner and you make a
dinner date and then suddenly you got
this hunky guy and you all sit down and
they're they're all
like you know and they're like is she is
he with her like is it her cousin or is
it a brother and then slowly over the
course of the dinner he's like hugging
you and giving you a Pex on the cheek
and they're like oh my my God that's her
boyfriend you know then
uh they're going to be like dang how did
she do that it's been five years she
even the ones she had before five years
ago were all losers you know and then
she got this guy and he's so intelligent
and sensitive and and then he will go to
the bathroom
okay hopefully it's a number two okay uh
cuz we need time to talk so he will
leave for the bathroom he'll say I have
to go to the bathroom and then every the
girls are all like and as soon as he's
out of earshot you know it's all what
are they going to say you know where's
the club or what kind of lipstick was it
Estee Lao or was
it I don't know any other ones any so
Sephora sells all of them come on Chanel
okay no they will ask you was it H&M was
it Chanel you know was it a club was it
a yog where's the yoga school where boys
like that are doing yoga you know what I
mean and then uh you're going to say
it's the nursing
home and then they're going to say what
you know what do you mean you know this
is where you hope it's a number two cuz
then you have time to talk about it and
you'll say I went to this talk the guy
said you had to plant kic seeds he
suggested going to a nursing home if you
don't want to be lonely you have to make
another person not lonely and that
plants a karmic seed and any one of you
can create your own man this way okay
two of them will try they will get a
boyfriend then the other three will try
because the two got one got it what's
happening it's a revolution no it's a
ground zero starts with you
you spiritual teaching
is in the end it's only
example it doesn't matter what you say
at
all people will do exactly what you do
good or bad they will copy you
unfortunately okay everything you do the
good thing and the bad thing your
students will copy you no matter what
you say don't do what I'm doing in the
next five minutes they'll do it within a
week okay it's the the only way to teach
spiritual things is by example okay you
have to be what you're talking about
okay if you get a beautiful incredible
partner by following some spiritual
means other people will copy you because
they're not dumb they want one too okay
I want what she's having you know what I
mean Sally and what's it called I love
that I'll have what she's having you
know and
uh think that during the visit to the
nursing home and it's bodh ch and it's
not selfish
anymore okay have that intention in your
mind and it's not uh it's not artificial
it's not forced it's the truth if this
works for me it's going to work for all
my friends and then their friends will
copy them we will be living
examples of this new idea of how to get
your dreams and that will spread and it
started with me I will I will be the
first person I will prove that it works
got it then it's not selfish anymore
then it's bodh it's the absolute
opposite of selfish got it that's
Universal compassion forget all
this forget it that's a bod ch right
that's bodh but it's not it's not this
right this is real buy CH and you don't
have to meditate for 6 years in the
desert to get it just trying to fulfill
your own
dreams in a karmic way and and thinking
you might set an example for others is
Bod it's real bodh and there's no other
bodh okay and it's for real and you can
do it and it's not some kind of thing
that only the Dil Lama has or something
like that don't think like that okay got
it then it's not selfish anymore then
the man is going to be
like he's going to want to save the
world with you which is by the way just
to let you know and then we'll stop
that's the way it all ends okay that's
where this all leads to okay you you
have a spiritual partner you both get
enlightened together as did Lord Buddha
with tillotama lady tillotama on the day
of his
Enlightenment it only came because of
his partnership and then they stepped
above the world and took care of the the
world they served they took care of the
whole world that became their
gig okay and it's always like that it
always ends like that okay what I'm
talking about always ends that way okay
you always end up taking care of a whole
planet or two actually a billion planets
but you won't believe
that okay
that's that's all I have to say about
Nana here okay very holy talk and true
talk just try okay get rid of your use
those four
steps okay just try all right you have
extra pressure because you are trying to
set an example for other people if you
succeed in being happy people will copy
you the hardest thing to do in the world
is to make yourself
happy and you can't teach other people
how to be happy if you're not
happy if you're obviously not together
it's pretty weird to be teaching other
people how to get their act together
okay uh if you're obviously really
happy then uh then you can help other
people okay so you're Duty your sacred
responsibility the highest
responsibility you have is to make
yourself
happy Isn't that
cool now that's how you're going to
serve people is make your make yourself
into a happy person okay then then
that's your job okay all right we'll
dedicate the karma
anyway
she
me
de
okay uh everyone would like to go home
and me
too uh but I think it's important that
we thank the people who served us and
made this possible so please sit still
and I I would like to also be able to
focus on thanking the people who who
work so hard to make this happen so I'm
going to ask
Nicole or
Robin thank you guys so much for being
part of this event um I'm really
impressed you guys are all Troopers
because I know you know we live in a
world now where there's actually like a
huge influx of Dharma teachings like
almost all the time
uh
and like a lot of you I've seen over and
over again and um you know we're all
juggling work and and training and all
these things and and you still make time
to come here and and attend and I can
tell that um there's really like nothing
that you guys wouldn't do if you knew it
served other people and I'm really
inspired so um thank you very much for
for coming it's such good company for
all of us um and and I'm really excited
to hear that you're coming back to New
York City
gisha um so I want to just make this
offering suggestion that uh uh we all
spend some time imagining how the time
we've spent here will like through all
of us the whole group like slowly Ripple
out into the world um and ask GHA
Michael to stay with you
um so you know we can build up these
clal clais habits and then when the
really challenging stuff does come up
because it will you know this is life um
we'll be able to respond in the way like
Gela would you
know yeah and he'll be guiding us that
during those really hard times so that's
what we wish gisha thank you very much
please keep
teaching um Robin buckon she oh my gosh
I she's amazing
fantastic event producer hire her if
you're looking for one definitely she
did such a great job and the entire work
study team would you guys including the
T would you all please stand up briefly
for a round of applause they work so
hard really so
hard
it was a
pleasure sure um when you uh so you
should have exchanged information with
your Tas like or they'll be emailing you
or you already have their email and you
should submit your homeworks to them and
they'll submit your grades to YSI for
safekeeping
um I'll also be inviting everyone to
everyone who signed up for the full
program to um the videos online again
we're happy to do that it worked out
really nicely last
time um and if you didn't get the second
part of the reading for tonight that got
passed out during the break make sure
you pick that up on your way out it has
the homework and the answer key I'd like
to give a hand to
ni
you are you're very
welcome I one more uh I'd like to thank
my own staff uh Mercedes BTO who also
sang so
beautifully uh her partner loan yumbo
where are
you
uh they travel with me constantly they
don't get any
sleep uh they die constantly they suffer
constantly and I'm really grateful to
them I couldn't do what I do without
them uh Venable Jigme
helps
uh and then just uh Christine W Nicole
friend Diane Nancy Kar Michael Wick anal
andriana Darcy Etc
Brooks thank you so much uh okay La uh
or okay no just kidding uh what's your
thing oh Sakura is in charge of the next
half would you please stand up
Moria like she's in charge of the
Bahamas
program so if you want to try to make it
to the Bahamas talk to her it's going to
be stressful for her but that's fine get
you get used to it
uh we are going to donate readings to
the 200 50 residents of the asham right
now down there and uh we decided it
would be cheaper to print them here
she's got
12,000 pages of printings she has
two uh printers to be carried down there
for the other readings that are not
written yet and I would like to ask for
four volunteers going to the Bahamas to
help her get there Nicole is one two
three it means you're going to carry in
your luggage one one one printer or
something okay did you get their names
can you see please see her afterwards
and don't leave her hanging okay cuz
it's kind of stressful and she's leaving
tomorrow morning right so uh so please
meet with her afterwards and help her
and then help her when we get down there
if you want to get in at the last minute
talk to her I think it's still humanly
possible but uh okay and we'll see you
thank you for coming and uh thank you
for letting me teach and I'd like to
also give lady Ruth a for
coming